[Music]
This program is brought to you by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.
Let's uh let's very quickly review and
then I want to move on to
some I think fairly somewhat difficult
concepts.
My purpose in teaching these
courses was to try to teach what I
called the theoretical minimum. The
minimum amount of stuff that you really
need if you truly want to technically be
able to go on to the next
step. The next step in this case uh
after general relativity might be
cosmology. And you really want to do it
right. But you don't want to do
everything. You don't want to do all the
applications. You don't want to learn
everything. You want to learn just
enough, the bare minimum, to be able to
go to the next step. Um, tonight I think
we're going to face the fact that the
bare minimum is already a little bit
complicated and requires some uh some
mathematical effort. It doesn't require
advanced mathematics. It just requires
patience to go through the calculations
and to do them right.
uh if I just told you in words what the
answers are, I think I would not be
giving you the minimum. I think I would
be giving you less than the minimum. So
today today may be a little bit trying
but bear with it. Uh what you get out of
it if you follow it will be worth the
effort. Okay, let's just go through the
definitions of the transformation
properties of the two kinds of
components covariant and
contravariant. If I have
a covariant set of
components, coariant means
lower. and they're now referring to a
coordinate system
y. Not only do I think of them as
functions of y, but I also think of them
as the components, the covariant
components relative to the coordinate
axes defined by the
y-coordinates. Okay. So this is V subm
in the ycoordinate system both with
respect to its components and with
respect to what it depends on
y. Those components can be expressed in
terms of the components in terms of some
other coordinate system. Here's some
other coordinate system x y and
x. Given the components, the covariant
components in one coordinate system, you
can translate them to the components in
another coordinate system. And here's
the formula that we worked out last time
that VM is related to VN of
X by multiplying it by
DX N by
DYM. We worked that out last time. These
are the set of objects that you use. And
keep in mind that the summation
convention is in force here. So summing
over n, the open index on this side is
m. So this side here is the mth
component of v. The n index here is
summed over. So it's just a dummy index.
But on both sides, you have an open
index m. And notice that that open index
m has to do with
y. It's the mth ycoordinate here. And on
the left hand side, this also has to do
with y because we're talking about the
components of the vector in the
y-coordinate system. The xcoordinate
system that's been summed over and uh it
appears only as a dummy index here. This
is the transformation
property of a vector. If it doesn't
transform this way, it's not called a
vector. Even if it has components, even
if you might try building up an arrow to
represent it, uh you know, there's no
question you can take
uh let's take the temperature, the
pressure and uh the humidity. There are
three numbers and I could now build
myself a arrow which along that axis has
a length equal to the temperature along
that axis has a length equal to the uh
humidity and so forth and so on. That
object is not a tensor. It is not a
vector. It's just a thing you made up
out of three scalers.
It's not a tensor
because the its components when you go
to a different reference frame don't
transform. Right? The temperature is the
temperature. It's the same in all
coordinate systems and it doesn't change
from one coordinate system to another.
So the temperature does not transform
like one of the components of a vector.
In fact, it transforms as a
scalar. All right. So uh any set of
three numbers or four numbers depending
on the dimensionality of the space is
not does not constitute a vector. A
vector is characterized by its
transformation properties. Given it in
one coordinate system, how do you get it
in the other? Likewise
uh I'm using V now as the generic term
for a vector not necessarily the same
vector. If I have a vector with
contravariant
indices, then it's related in the
y-coordinate system to its to the
corresponding values in the xcoordinate
system by
a similar
formula, but now it's dy by
dx. And now the n goes downstairs and
the m goes
upstairs. Look at the equation. Look at
the equations. You can't make a mistake
about whether it's dx dy or
dydx. If you're talking about a thing
with a covariant index here, it's got to
match with a contravariant index
here. On the left hand side, you have a
covariant m. On the right hand side, you
have a covariant m. And what's more, the
covariant m on this side has to do with
y. So the covariant m on this side has
to do with y. So you can bet your boots
that the that this one is going to be X
and the upstairs. Same here on on the
left hand side you have a contravariant
index M an upstairs index M associated
with the Ycoordinates and that's why you
have an upstairs index here also
associated with the y-coordinates. So
there's a pattern that's the pattern of
um transformation properties of a
vector. I won't bother writing down the
transformation properties of a scalar.
They don't transform. They're the same
in every coordinate system.
Yeah. I think I'm a little confused
about you said that if it's a vector, it
has to satisfy that top equation.
Yeah.
Satisfy the second equation. No, there
are don't identify this set of objects
with this set of objects yet. This is
just this is just some covariant vector.
Remember I had I gave you some example
of a coariant vector. The gradient the
derivative of a scalar with respect to a
coordinate is a covariant
vector. Don't try to think of now uh of
the connection between covariant and
converter. They're different objects for
the moment. So I shouldn't have called
them by the same uh by the same letter.
I just don't want to run out of letters.
So I'll call them both V. We can let's
not let's call it W.
Okay, this is the transformation
property of a covariant object. This is
the transformation property of a
contravariant object. And they're not
the same thing. Uh here's a covariant
vector. An example of a contravariant
vector would just be a small
displacement
dx
m dx and dy
representing a small little
displacement. Well, dx sorry dx1 and dx2
dx1 and dx2. Let's see here's the x
coordinates. Let's say this one is x1.
Let's say this one is x2. You build
yourself a vector by going
off and making an excursion along the x1
axis by dx1 and then along the x2 axis
by x2. And the
resultant is the vector that we can just
call
dx. The vector that we call dx has
components which are
contravariant. Right? They're
contravariant indices. The the
components of a gradient are covariant.
And you can't go wrong. If you remember,
the only only rule you have to remember
is that coordinates carry their indices
upstairs. That's an arbitrary rule. It
could have been the other way. Uh but
it's an arbitrary rule. I'm not sure
whom it's due to, but you label the
coordinates x1, x2, x3 with
superscripts. And once you do that, it's
hard to go
wrong. Here's a superscript on an M, but
it's downstairs in the denominator of
something. It just looks like it has to
do with something with lower indices.
And in fact, it is true that this can be
thought of as the gradient vector. Let
me call it V again. V subm. It's a
covariant vector. dx has its indices
upstairs. It's a contravariant vector.
Now the transformation properties came
from the transformation properties of
this
object. Right? Let's let's just
see if our if the vector we're talking
about is a
gradient then this equation just says
that partial of phi with respect to ym
that's the left hand side
here because the ve because v is a
gradient that's equal on the right hand
side we have partial of phi with respect
to x whoops
xym n that's this object times dx
n by
dyn dy m is this a correct
equation? Yeah, that's a correct
equation. d5 by dy is d5 by dx * dx by
dy.
This equation didn't come from the
definition of any vector or covariant
contravariant. It just came from
elementary calculus that the gradient
with respect to y is just equal to the
gradient with respect to x times the set
of components dx dy. That's uh that's
elementary calculus elementary
multivariable
calculus
but it's the place that we abstracted
this rule. If I now call this V M sorry
V M and this one
VN then that's my rule.
Likewise the transformation property of
the contravariant vectors came from the
statement that
dym is equal to the partial of
ym with respect to
xn time
dxn. Again, this here had did not come
from somebody's preconceived notion
about how tensors should transform. It's
just a calculus
fact. Uh what is there? Some sort of
chain rule. They're both some sort of
chain rules, I guess.
Um and now if I replace dy mm by wm and
dxn by wn
here that defines or this defines the
transformation property of a coar
contravariant vector that's where they
came from. So covariant and
contravariant mean things that transform
the same way as gradients on the one
hand and differentials differential
displacements. Differential
displacements and
uh and gradients those are the sort of
archetypes of uh coariant and
contravariant objects.
uh
blah we can have more complicated
objects with any number of indices. The
transformation properties of objects
with more indices are similar. Let me
just give you an
example. Let's here's an here's a
transformation property of a covariant
expression. Supposing I have a
tensor with two indices let's say m and
r then the rule is for each index for
each
index there's a factor of a dx by dy and
here's the way it works this is t in the
ycoordinates we're going to relate it to
t in the x coordinates
not m but we better choose some new uh
let's uh let's let's call it
ns and now just as over here to relate
the m index to the n index we need dx
this is a sort of operation which takes
us from an n index to an m
index we do exactly that dxn by
dym but that works on the first index
here we also need to work on the second
index and that's
dxs by
dyr. Now look at it on the right hand
side we have the components of the
tensor that the se the rank two tensor
two indices in the x coordinates
two lower indices those lower indices
have to do with x. So on the right hand
side oh sorry it must multiply something
with contravariant
indices again referring to x but on the
left hand side we have covariant indices
referring to y likewise on this side
over
here that's the
pattern indices are the things which
transform yeah could you mix them make
any sense how how would you want to fix
some upper and some lower. Yes,
certainly. For example, you could have a
All right, let's let's do another
example. Supposing we had a
tensor which had one lower index and one
upper
index. Perfectly good object. How does
it transform? Well, we should have I
should not have erased the
transformation properties of the things
with upper indices here. Let me write
them down over
here. So,
uh yeah, here's for the lower index m
and let me uh change variable here.
Let's call it
rr. And now let's write the
transformation property of an upper
index. And that's going to be
dyn by
dxs
vs. All right. So here's the thing with
a lower index. Here's a thing with an
upper index. Here's an object, a tensor
with a lower index and an upper index.
Right? How does it transform? Well, just
first of all, we have to work on the m
index. That's going to give us a dxr by
dym.
And then we have to work on the upper
index. That will give us a dy by
dxs times
t. Now let's see what is it. t
uh the upper index is s and the lower
index is uh is
r. All right.
So that's the transformation properties
of a thing with an upper and lower index
and it's just borrowed. It's just
exactly the same as if you just stuck
this thing next to this
thing and thought of a tensor as just a
product VM VN on the left hand side. V
MVN referred to the Ycoordinates on the
right hand side
VRVS related to the Y-coordinates.
Right? So that's the uh that's the
transformation property of a mixed
tensor with some upper and some lower
indices and the general rule for any
number of indices is
similar. Okay, that's
that without this set of rules it would
be hopeless to try to explain um the
geometry of even a simple thing like a
sphere in any great detail. But
certainly a general geometry of
arbitrary curvature, wiggles and so
forth hopeless uh without uh tensors. So
tensors are the key to understanding the
geometry of curved
spaces. Okay, let me point let's let's
do something else.
Let's take a
tensor which happens to have yes let's
take this tensor which happens to have
an upper and lower
index and now let's identify and sum the
upper index with the lower index in
other words let's take
tmm that
means
t11 plus
t22 plus t3 3 three however many
dimensions of space I have t one lower
and one upper index this is a legal
operation to combine or to identify an
upper index with a lower index and sum
over them I don't need to write the
summation sign I claim that this
object with the indices identified and
then summed how many indic what indices
does this whole object have does it have
any
indices no it has no indices left over.
They've been summed over. It doesn't
have a T1. It doesn't have this. It's
just a pure thing. It's a sum and it
doesn't have any leftover indices. What
kind of thing is it likely to be? A
scaler. All right, let's check that it
really is a
scalar. All we have to do is identify M
with N. Let's do it over here. Set M
equal to N or N equal to M. We better do
it over here also. I've set n equal to
m and
sum.
Now what do we have here? We have the
change in xr when we vary y times the
change in y when we vary xs. What is
this whole object
here? Anybody know? That's the chronica
delta. It's the chronica delta. It's
really just the derivative of xr with
respect to
xs. The derivative of xr with respect to
ym times the derivative of ym with
respect to xs summed over m is the same
as the derivative of xr with respect to
xs. Just cancel out the yn. Well, what's
the derivative of xr with respect to
xs? Like it's like having three
coordinates x, y, and z. The derivative
of x with respect to x is one. The
derivative of x with respect to y is
zero. All right? So this is a number
which is
one when r is the same as s and zero
otherwise. In other words, it's just the
chronica delta.
We could replace this and replace it by
the chronica delta delta rs one when r
is equal to s zero when r is not equal
to s. But now we're supposed to sum over
r and s. What will that give
us? It'll just give us the sums of t11
plus t22 plus t33.
Again, whenever you see a chronica
delta, it's really just an a a shorthand
or it's just an instruction to set r
equal to
s. Why? Because it's one if r equals s
and it's zero otherwise. So, it's just
an instruction. You can throw it away
and in the rest of the expression set r
equal to
s. So, look what we have. we have tmm of
y equals
trr of
x. In other words, this particular
combination doesn't depend on which
coordinate system you use.
The
dependence of the components on
coordinate system cancel out when you
identify the upper index and the lower
index and some that's a general pattern.
If I have some
tensor, let's call it W, with a whole
bunch of
indices, MN,
MNR,
PQ, I don't know what's another
letter. Z, that's a terrible notation.
You're not supposed to do that. MNR. And
now that's that's a tensor with six
indices. A six rank tensor with three
contra uh three covariant and three
contravariant indices. Let me make it a
little general. Let's make a different
number of upper indices and lower
indices. So a four upper indices and
three lower indices. Now if I identify
an upper index with a lower index for
example replace Z by M and
sum the result is a
tensor with three upper indices and two
lower
indices. That's a pattern. You prove it
the same way as I prove this that when
you identify upper and lower indices and
sum over them, what's left over the
index structure that's left over after
you've summed over
m the components still transform as a
tensor in this case with three upper
indices and two lower indices. So that's
a process that you can do on a
tensor that creates another tensor of
lower rank smaller number of indices.
For example, if you
construct a tensor out of two vectors,
let's construct let's take two vectors V
and
W. Let's suppose V has upper indices and
W has lower indices.
That's a tensor, just a product. In
other words, the components are simply
the products of components. We call that
TMN. If I then identify M with N and
[Music]
sum that defines a scalar. What is that
scaler called?
That's a dotproduct of two vectors. It's
the inner product, sometimes called the
inner product between two vectors.
So the inner product and and even better
supposing they're the same
vector. Well, we haven't defined what it
means for them to be the same vector. So
far, things with upper components are
simply different than things with lower
components. Yeah. Can we therefore say
that that W you've expressed there with
seven indices is equal to a scaler times
w n a no no it's not a scale no it's not
a scaler times that that it could be
depending on the uh on the character of
this uh tensor it could be that but it's
it's not typically a product no but when
you do contract this is called
contracting the indices this process is
called contracting the indices m when
you contract the index m It simply
lowers the rank of the t tensor and the
remaining objects do form a tensor.
Doesn't mean that this w here is some
scalar
times wn
a you know nr a
pq. It does not mean
that in general that won't be
true.
Uh what's that in general? No, it's not
equal to
that. It may be equal to that in a
special case. That's a special case. But
in general, it's not
true. So yeah,
when you have one vector, when you have
one index, you have vectors. When you
have two indexes, does that correspond
to planes or anything? Yeah, it
corresponds to planes. Yeah. But uh
um sometimes it corresponds to
planes. The tensor that we got a little
bit familiar with last time, the rank
two tensor was the metric tensor. The
metric tensor has a geometric meaning.
It's simply related to the distance
between neighboring points. Neighboring
points mean points which are
separated
by differential
distances. All right. So if I
have a a set of differentials
dxm then that corresponds to two
neighboring points and we can ask what's
the diff what's the distance what's the
distance between them? The actual
distance the distance between them
squared is called ds squared and it's
given by dxm
dxn times the metric tensor gmn of
x. Now notice this is a special case of
the rule of contracting indices. We've
contracted m with m and n with n. There
are no leftover indices.
This is a
scalar. Two contravariant indices, two
covariant
indices. And the metric tensor is the
object which allows you to compute if
you know it, you know, if you know it,
uh it allows you to compute
the distance between neighboring
points. Now, is G really a tensor? Let's
check. To check, we have to see how it
transforms. All right. To see how it
transforms, we need to write the
distance between the same two points,
but instead of in x notation, in y
notation. So all we need to do is write
that
dxm is equal to the derivative of xm
with respect to y r
dyr. Right? The change in xm is just or
the the differential displacement in xm
is the derivative of xm with respect to
y r times the differential displacement
in y. If I plug that in for both x dxm
and dxn, what will I find? I'll find
that this is the derivative of xm with
respect to y r. That's for this one.
Then this one
dxn by
dys times g
mn times
uh d y d
yr
dys. All right. I've just here's GMN
that's still there. GMN of
X that's still there. DXM and DXN I've
each replaced by DX by DY times the
corresponding
dy each one of them XM and DXN. And now
if I take this whole thing
here and call it GRS of
Y then my formula real reads that
ds^2 is equal to grs of y d y r
dys. In other words, we've discovered
that G that G in the Ycoordinate system
is G in the Xcoordinate system times
these familiar factors which are the
standard factors for the transformation
of covariant
indices. So this is the simple
illustration that the metric tensor is
indeed a tensor.
If you express the distance in either
the x coordinates or the
ycoordinates, you'll wind up with a grs
of y or a gr or gmn of x. And they are
related by this transformation
property. So that's uh that's the notion
of the metric tensor. Now there's
another important thing that goes with
the metric tensor.
Second rank tensors like this are
matrices. They have two indices. They
are
matrices.
G think of G
MN at an arbitrary point. And I won't
label the
point. It's it's a matrix. I can put
G11, G12,
G13, G21, G22,
G23, G31, dot dot dot, and so
forth. It's a
matrix. It's
symmetric. It's symmetric. G12 is equal
to
G21. and it has an inverse. This is
something you can
prove. Matrices have inverses. What does
it mean that a matrix has an inverse? It
means there's another matrix that you
can multiply it by to get the unit
matrix. What is the unit matrix in this
notation?
Incidentally, the unit matrix in this
notation is of course the matrix one one
one one with all
zeros. That's a matrix which is is what?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Well, however many
components there are. Yeah. Yeah. The
unit matrix is the
matrix which every component is either
zero if m is not equal to
n or one if m is equal to n. In other
words, it's the matrix
representing the chronica delta symbol
delta mn.
Let's not write equals. Let's
write say it again.
Should the M and N and the delta both be
lower?
No. The chronica delta in relativity
theory always has one index upper and
one index
lower. Uh if ever you have a formula
with two lower indices and it says delta
MN, either you're doing something
special and unusual and not following
the usual conventions, which is okay.
You're allowed to. I mean you're allowed
to break conventions if you need
to. Uh but it means it's not associated
with a tensor. It's not a tensor
operation. Uh so delta n m its
components are also a tensor. Now to say
that there's another matrix let's call
this matrix let's just call it G. Let's
not indicate any indices at all and
let's just think of it as a matrix.
There's another matrix which is the
inverse
matrix and a product of the two matrices
are the unit
matrix in index
notation to write that in index notation
it's
g let's call it
um let me not let's call it r
N G
inverse and
now M
R here's the rule the standard rule for
contracting
indices take a upper index here now so
far I haven't told you that the I'm
telling you now the thing The inverse
matrix defines a tensor. The components
of the inverse matrix define a tensor
with upper indices with contravariant
indices. This is not obvious. This is
not obvious. It's a theorem. I would
look it up if uh you
want look up the theorem that the
inverse of the metric thought of as a
matrix is itself also a tensor or also
defines a set of components which are
tensor
components. Now this operation here of
contracting R and summing over R is
matrix
multiplication. So this is the process
of matrix multiplication. It gives
another matrix with an index m and an
index n. I've summed over r. The right
hand side here is the identity matrix
which is the chronica
delta m n. That's the definition of the
inverse matrix here. It's the thing
which when you multiply it by g with
lower indices and then contract one
index, you get the chronica delta.
Let's see if we can find
it. First of all, yeah, let's take the
um let's take
the polar coordinates. Take polar
coordinates. Polar coordinates. We had
the metric
ds^2 is equal to um the r 2 plus r 2
sin^ 2 theta uh no sorry r 2 d theta^
2. All right. What's g11 in this
case? Let's say r corresponds to the
first coordinate. Theta corresponds to
the second
coordinate just
one. What about
G22? R
squ 0 0. No off diagonal elements at
all. This is G
MN. What about its inverse? Its inverse
in this case is very simple. When you
have a diagonal matrix, if you have a
diagonal matrix, it's
inverse. Say it again. I was wondering
whe R
R squ
in the Yep. It's R
squ. You don't square
G. Yeah. The um the components of the
metric are already squared lengths. They
already correspond to squared
lengths.
Yeah. The inverse matrix, the matrix
that's inverse to
that is just one 1 / r
2. If you multiply the two matrices
together, you'll get the unit matrix. If
you think of them as objects with
indices and
contract the R index, you'll get the
chronica delta. Try it out. Check it
out. This inverse of the
metric, right? I don't know that it has
an I don't think it has a special name
of its own. It's just called the metric
with contravariant components. It's
called the collection of contravariant
components of the metric. If you know
one of them, you know the other. If you
know a matrix, you know its inverse. The
inverse of the inverse is the original
matrix. So knowledge of G with lower
indices is equivalent to knowledge of G
with upper indices. The theorem, and
this is not a trivial
theorem, is and I'm not going to do it
on the blackboard. The theorem is that
the set of components of the inverse
matrix are themselves a tensor. They're
a tensor with contravariant
components. So if you take the metric
and you invert it as a matrix, it's a
collection of components. Those
components form a contravariant tensor.
It's another representation of the
metric since it has the same information
in it, but it's just presented in a
different way. Those two objects are
fundamental. G with lower indices and G
with upper indices. And we don't bother
writing the inverse there. We just
remember that when G is written with
upper indices, it's the inverse matrix
to the ones with lower indices. And so
the identity
the uh identity in the sense of a of the
equation
gmrn is delta mn. This is if you like
the definition of the object with
contravariant
components. It's a
um and its geometric meaning is a little
more obscure. The geometric meaning of
this object is clear. It has to do with
the separation between points. This
object you'll just get familiar with.
You'll get to use it and you'll see it
does some uh some useful
things. All right, that's the idea of
the metric tensor and its inverse or the
metric tensor with covariant indices and
and the metric tensor with contravariant
indices.
Now once you
have this metric in covariant and
contravariant form you can start playing
games and write mappings that relate
covariant and contravariant vectors. In
fact, you can define for every covariant
vector or for every set of
covariant components, you can define a
set of contravariant components and
think of it as contravariant and
covariant components of the same vector.
Here's the rule. If I give
you a set of covariant
components, I can construct from it from
it together with the metric tensor.
Well, let's let's start with
contravariant. Let's start with
contravariant.
I can construct from it and the metric
an object with a lower
index by multiplying it by GMN and
summing over M. That gives me a new
thing which I'll call V subn.
If I know V with a
superscript and I know the metric. Let's
say the metric is given. Metric is given
knowledge. It's a piece of the geometry
of space. If I know V and I know G, then
I can reconstruct a corresponding set of
components with lower
indices. You can just think of this as
the representation of the same vector
except with a lower index. Now what is
the connection between them really? I'll
tell you now the connection between them
is what I told you in the first place.
The connection between these two things
is if
vM are the set of coefficients that you
multiply by unit vectors and sum them
up to get the vector v.
If you think of these V's here as
defining a vector by adding up the V's
times unit
vectors, then the V's with lower
components are, as I told you in the
beginning, the co-variant
uh components of the same vector. In
other words, the projections onto the
axes. These are the set of coefficients
that you use to expand the vector. These
are the set of
orthogonal projections onto the axes. So
they're really representations of the
same object, two different
representations and they're related in
this form.
Question. Yeah. Um going back to the
other word, can't there be tensors that
don't have inverses? There are, but the
metric tensor is never one of them.
Um let's not prove that now. Uh it
follows from the fact that G is
symmetric and that there are no
directions in which
the in which
uh the
vector has no length at all. there are
no zero igen values of the uh of the
metric, right? But that's a good
question. It's a fair question. Let's
just take it as a rule that the metric
tensor always has an inverse and we'll
see. I'll come back to it. I'll I'll
prove it for you another day. I hadn't
thought about it, but it's uh it's an
easy thing to prove. Yeah. Is that also
true in relativistic?
Yeah, it is. It is. It is. It's still
true. Yeah. The upper board there It can
be shown on the left. The upper board on
the left. It can be shown, right? The S
squares are the same regardless of the
coordinates. Distance is in fact the
same. Wait, say it again. The distance
will be the same regardless of the
coordinates. It's not obvious in the
expression, but I assume it can be
shown.
Wait, that the DS squares are the same.
DS is the same whether you comput it
with the GM or the G. No,
that's that is that is where we got the
we assumed that to find the relationship
between GMN of X and GRS of
Y. In other words, I simply took this
and rewrote it in this way. Really the
same equation. It's really the same
equation. Yeah. Given that the G's are
related as they have to be related uh by
tensor transformation properties.
Yeah. Yeah.
You said that G was symmetric. Is that
clear from what uh good question. All
right. So let's see what it would mean
for them to not be symmetric and then
see why. The answer is it doesn't matter
whether you choose them to be symmetric
or not. But let's see why. All right.
What does g12 m
multiply? g12 multiplies dx1 dx2,
right? What does g21
multiply? Multiplies dx2
dx1. But really what that means is that
the only thing that comes in when you
when you calculate the s squared is g12
plus
g21 dx1
dx2 only the combination g12 plus g21
enters into
anything. That means you can take g21
and g12 to be equal to each other and
sort of divide it symmetrically between
the x1. There's a piece in the metric
which has dx1 multiplying
dx2, right? You could call it all coming
from g12 if you like or you could all
call it all coming from g21. But the
convention is to split it equally
between g12 and g21 and therefore make
the g
symmetric. So it's partly a convention
but it's a useful a useful
convention and
uh and
and right
so the general rule be that g12 is not
the same thing as
g21 generaliz you could imagine
generalizing that things that way but
then the the difference the the
non-ymmetric piece would never come into
anything right uh it would supposing g12
2 and G21 were the negative of each
other, then this would just cancel out
and say you just wrote something
redundant that you didn't need. So, uh
there's no loss of generality in taking
it to be symmetric, but you don't have
to take it to be
symmetric. If you don't take it to
cement it to be symmetric, it's not
clear there's always an inverse matrices
with
um
uh well I I'll come back I'll come back
to the question of the inverse next
time. I don't want to I don't want to
interrupt the interrupt it right
now. Okay.
So the metric allows you to play new
games where you take tensors and shift
the index from upstairs to downstairs
and think of them as the same object
except covariant components and
contravariant components. It allows you
to find a onetoone correspondence
between a set
of contravariant components and a set of
covariant components and you're free to
think of them as the same thing since
they have the same information.
Incidentally, you can solve this
equation for the upper components. This
is the lower components written in terms
of the upper components. See if you can
prove using the property where is
it? Using only the property that G what
is it? M R
GRN equals
delta RN.
Oh uh
sorry
eminent. Eminem
uh see if you can prove it's very
straightforward that you can solve this
as VM
equals G MN with upper index time
VN. Really all it is is another way of
writing uh in matrix language it would
be G * ah do it do it do it do it. It
follows immediately from this uh
equation over here. Okay.
Uh
right. Yeah. All you have to do is take
VN from this equation, plug it into
here, and you'll get an identity that VM
equals VM. You do it. Okay. So you can
go back and forth symmetrically between
things with upper indices and lower
indices and the process is called
raising and lowering indices of
tensors. So every tensor has multiple
identities uh in which you can raise and
lower any of the indices at will keep
track of them. Keep track of which ones
you've lowered and which ones you you've
raised. uh for example if I have a
general tensor
tmn I can raise the index m how would I
do that I would multiply it
by gm
r
t
rn I've taken the first index the first
index on the left here and I've applied
the trick to the first index to raise
it. And what does this give me? This
gives me an object that I can call TM
N. So I can raise and lower the
indices. And of course, the objects that
you get are different when you raise and
lower them, but they're collections of
objects which have the same content as
the original starting one since you can
go back and forth freely between
them. All right, that's the sense in
which vectors have in which a a vector
has both covariant and contravariant
indices. All
right, that's uh that is
basic tensor
arithmetic, tensor algebra, I guess one
would
say, upper indices, lower
indices, transformation properties of
the indices, and the metric tensor that
allows you to raise and lower indices.
Uh let's uh let's
yeah in
particular take the object
dxm that stands for a little
interval
dx a little
vector I can assign it the and it's
natural to think of the little interval
as having contravariant
components but you could also define an
object dx
subm the same vector by writing it as g
mn
dxn the natural thing to define to start
with is the contravariant components
those are just the little intervals
dx but then nothing prevents you from
constructing the co-variant version of
the same object and this is the way you
would do it now Before I told I told you
earlier that if you have an upper index
and a lower index in a tensor you can
contract them. So let's take a new
tensor. Let's take a tensor which has an
upper and lower index and it's made just
by multiplying dxm by
dxn. That is now an
object with indices m and
n. It's a
tensor. And now I want to contract the
index m with
n and get
dxm
dxm. What happens when you take a tensor
with two indices, one upper and one
lower, and you contract them? What do
you get? a scalar. So this object is a
scaler. But now let's rewrite it. Let's
rewrite it by using that dx with the
lower m is g mn dxn. That means that
this object here is
dxm.
Well, let's uh let's change let's
um yeah, let's write it this way. N
Yeah, no, it was right. The xm
It's clearly dxm
dxn
gmn. This object is just a dx with the
lower
index. I've lowered the index of dxn
that's here. And I multiply it by
another dx. So what is this object with
dxm upper and one dx lower contracted?
is gmn dxm dxn. What is
that? It's the s squ. It's the distance
between
them. So by using the metric tensor to
lower the index, you can write the
distance formula in two distinct
ways. You can write it gmn dxm
dxn or you can just write it dxm
dxm one lower and one upper. Same
thing. This is a little more condensed.
This is a little more explicit.
Would you go back over that first
equation you wrote? DX MC.
Yeah. Yes.
Uh, sorry, I didn't mean to write
equals. I just
meant goes to by contracting the indic
by contracting the indices. I did not
mean to write an equation. I simply
meant that you could contract the index
m and n and construct the x with
superscript the x with a subscript and
this is a
scalar. Okay, this doesn't transform.
It's an invariant quantity. whereas the
things that it was built out of
transformed but then you contracted the
index and got a
scala. Okay, so there's two distinct
ways. Uh in fact there's another way
that you could
write the
metric. Another way you could write it,
a third way is to write two lower
indices dxm dxn and that what would I
have to multiply it by?
G with upper
indices.
Indeed, that's also equal to the same
thing. They're all equal to each other
and they're all equal to the distance
between the
the points which are separated by the
differential displacements
dx. All right, that's the basic idea of
the metric and simple
relationship
where say it again
orthogonal projections now is there
MN in the top equation the bottom
equation lower GMN both those is there
any correlation between those the upper
and the lower
here the G GMn and then the GMN the
third equation oh they're all summation
indices so it doesn't matter what you
call
Yeah, as long as it's summed over, it
doesn't matter what you call them.
But is there a relationship in the
values of them? Like are they like
inverses?
Well, this is the inverse matrix to
this. So, you have to know how to
construct inverses of
matrices. All right. For simple diagonal
matrices, the inverses are easy. You
just turn the uh the entries upside
down. For things with off diagonal
elements, it's more complicated and you
have to uh consult the book or use a
computer program or uh or
whatever. And in particular uh for 4x4
matrices, it's uh it's no picnic.
for 2x2 matrices it's always
easy but
um good all right so that
that takes us through tensor
arithmetic tensor algebra incidentally
there are some other operations you can
do with tensors that may give you
tensors I haven't exhausted all the
operations that you can do that give you
uh tensors. You can add
tensors, add two tensors, but when you
do, you better make sure they're tensors
of the same type. In other words, you
would not want to
add
tmn plus
wn. That's a nonsense expression. It has
no distinct transformation properties.
This transforms one way. This transforms
the other way. For example, if this
happened to be zero in one set of
coordinates, it might not be zero in
another set of coordinates because the
t's with the lower indices don't
transform the same way.
If a tensor if a tensor is zero, if its
components are all zero in one
coordinate system, there's zero in all
coordinate systems. Why is that? Let's
just look at the sorts of things.
Well, that's because if we have a tensor
with any number of indices upstairs and
downstairs in the
ycoordinates, it is equal to a bunch of
dxs times dys and dys times dx's of
various kinds times the corresponding
tensor in the x
coordinates. If it's zero on one side,
it's zero on the other side.
So if a tensor is zero, in other words,
if the tensor being zero means all of
its components, if all of its components
are
zero, then it follows they are zero in
every coordinate system. So a tensor
being zero is an invariant statement
about that
tensor. All right. Another way to say
the same
thing, perhaps it's saying something a
little different, but almost the same
thing, is that if two tenses are equal
in one coordinate system, let's say t=
w
mn in the x
coordinates. That also says of course
that the difference between them is
equal to zero. then the difference is
going to be zero in every coordinate
system which means that the tensors are
equal in every coordinate system. So
once you prove a tensor
relationship namely that the left hand
side of an equation is equal to the
right hand side of an equation in one
set of coordinates it's true in every
set of coordinates. That's one of the
power that's one of the powerful things
about tensors that it allows you to make
um statements such as one thing is equal
to
another. Uh although
each side of the equation may have
complicated transformation properties,
you can be assured that both before and
after the transformation they will
remain equal. But that that may not have
come out right. You can be sure that if
they are equal in one coordinate system,
they will be equal in the other
coordinate system. That's part of the
power of
uh of
uh the equality of tensors is a
geometric fact which doesn't depend on
the coordinate system. The components of
the tensors are things which do depend
on the coordinate
system. Okay. Now let's take a little
bit of a break and then come to C to
tensor
calculus which is harder than tensor
arithmetic and tensor
algebra. I was going to
start the subject that I call tensor
calculus which means the study of how
you differentiate
tensors. Of course, you can just
differentiate them, but then it's not
clear that you get tensors when you
differentiate the components of a
tensor. And in fact, you don't. You have
to do something smarter than just
differentiate the components of the
tensor to get the
component. The derivatives of the
components of tensors are not ordinarily
components of tensors. Did that make
sense?
The derivatives of components are not
themselves components of tensors.
Derivatives with respect to what?
Position. X's.
X's. But
um I think I won't do that now. I think
instead we'll do that next time. And I
think I would like to get to spacetime.
We've been talking about space, space,
space. And we have not been talking
about relativity. We've been talking
about space. So, I think we we were all
set up in a way that allows us uh to uh
to
jump straight into
spacetime. And then somebody asked me
what the meaning of saying that the
universe is expanding. What does that
mean? And I think we can probably do
that yet tonight
uh once we introduce the idea of
spacetime. Now to introduce the idea of
spacetime we have to go back to special
relativity.
Special relativity is a
subject that you can
learn in three days. I assume that we
all know it. And if not, we can all
learn it uh
quickly. I
think if you've been in my class, you've
taken special relativity a couple of
times already, at least uh two times,
maybe more. And I'm going to assume that
you have a basic understanding of Lorent
transformations.
Um, but even if
not, I think we're set up in a manner
that uh that uh allows us
to sort
of make quick work of
it. Uh, first let me just make some
remarks about ordinary space.
Even if I am only going to use even if I
am not interested in curvy linear
coordinates or curved space all I'm
interested in now is cartisian
coordinates there are still more than
one cartisian coordinate system that we
can use to describe
space even if I don't even if I place
the origin of coordinates and nail it to
the center of some place. There's my
origin of coordinates. I still have not
fully specified
uh a set of coordinates by saying
they're cartisian. Here's a set of
cartisian
coordinates. Here's another set. Well, I
meant to I meant to place the origin at
the intersection of uh of the axes.
Here's another set.
Can that be
seen? Let me
uh and they're just related by rotation
of the coordinates of
course. Rotation of rotation of
cartisian coordinates is a special case
of transformations between x coordinates
and y-coordinates. Another thing you can
do is translate the coordinate systems.
Keep them parallel but uh translate
their locations. Those are also
coordinate transformations. In neither
case do they correspond to curved
coordinates, curvy linear coordinates,
but they are coordinate
transformations. And
um all of the rules we've set up up till
now hold. The only thing is that in all
of these coordinate systems, the metric
tensor has the same form. The metric
tensor is just the chronica delta. In
other
words,
ds^2 let's talk about two dimensions for
a moment is just equal to dx1^
2 plus
dx2. That's the same as saying that the
metric tensor
GMN is equal to the chronica delta delta
MN. Now I said that strictly speaking
delta MN with both of its indices lower
is not a good tensor object. It is a
good tensor if only if all we're doing
is translating between one set of cart
cartisian coordinates and another.
For curvy linear coordinates, this
equation would be
nonsense. But if we're just translating
between cartisian coordinate systems,
just rotating them or translating them,
then in every such coordinate system,
the metric is just dx1^ 2 plus dx2,
which I can also write as delta
mn
dxm dxn.
In cartisian coordinates, there's no
difference between upper indices and
lower indices. They're the same things.
So, uh there's a lot of
simplification. But there's another way
to say this that the transformations the
class of transformations that takes you
from one coordinate system to another
are the transformations which preserve
the
form of the interval. preserve the form
of the length preserve the form of
Pythagoras's
theorem right that the s squ the length
of a an interval is the x squ and what
happens if I have more components I just
add more of them in the x3 squ and so
forth so the ordinary transformations
that you can do on cartisian coordinates
are the
transformations which preserve the form
of the simple
the x sums of the x squares as the
length interval. Now let me come to
spacetime as you know and if you don't
you better find out
quickly
spacetime
has four coordinates. It's a
four-dimensional space. One of the
coordinates is
time. Incidentally, we are always going
to work in units in which the speed of
light is equal to one.
Now there's a
notion in special relativity of the
proper time or of the interval
separating two
points space and time we'll work with
speed of light equal one except when I
say that we won't and we can consider
two points for example these could be
two points on the trajectory theory of a
particle. There's a notion that we've
discussed in previous quarters of the
idea of the proper time the proper time
interval between two points which is
very similar but not a little different
but very similar to the distance between
two points. But you might expect if you
were naive that uh let's say there's
only two dimensions, one coordinate uh
one space coordinate and one time
coordinate. You might write ds^2 is
equal to dt
^2 plus
dx^2 and you could write that that's a
possible definition of something but
it's not the right thing for relativity
theory in particular the lorren
transformations the things which
transform you from one frame of
reference to another are not the things
are not the transformations which keep
this invariant
But keep something else invariant. What
is it?
dt ^2 minus
dx^2. And that's called the proper
time. Often labeled by dau^
2. If we insist on taking the speed of
light not to be one, then the speed of
light goes into this
equation in the denominator over
here. But in special
relativity, not using C equals 1 is as
stupid as using meters for X components
of vectors and inches for Y components.
If you did so, think about what your
equations would look like. You would
have some crazy
factors appearing all over the place.
First of all, your equations would not
look rotation invariant and they would
have all over the places peculiar
numbers which were simply the conversion
factor for the units that you use for X
dimensions and for Y dimensions and Z
dimensions. The speed of light is very
much like that. It's a conversion
factor from units of length to units of
time. Choosing C equals to one is the
natural analog of using the
same units for X measurements as Y
measurements. Notice incidentally uh if
I talked about the distance between two
points and I measured X in different
units than Y will the difference between
would the distance be dx plus dy^ 2?
Let's suppose I measure y in inches and
x in uh let's say feet and feet and now
I want the distance between those two
points in feet. What would I have to put
there? If I want the distance in the ds
if I want it in feet and x is measured
in feet then I'll have the x squ. But
what about the y^2? y is measured in
inches.
12,
right? Plus dy^2 / 144. You have a
stupid factor of 1 over 144 multiplying
the d y^2 term. Basically the same uh
the same silly factor that's here.
If you use units in which the speed of
light is equal to one, it's the same
thing as using meters or inches for the
Yeah. I think I've read somewhere that
particle physicists use units in which
electron volts everything
uh volts.
Yes. Well, you can
how does that work?
You need you need the plunks
constant which
uh isn't in here yet. The speed of light
rel look normally you say there are
three distinct uh units that you need
length, time and
mass. Okay. Now given that the speed of
light is equal to one or assuming the
speed of light is equal to one
eliminates one of
these. Setting plunk's constant equal to
one will allow you to write masses in
the same units as you use length and
time. All right? But we're not going
there today. We're not going to quantum
mechanics today. Today we're just going
to set C equal to one.
So and now Lorent
transformations and the special theory
of relativity is simply the theory of
transformations or coordinate systems
which preserve this form dt ^2 minus
dx^2 coordinate transformations
space-time coordinate
transformations which preserve the form
of the metric. This metric now
represents proper time not
uh
uh not uh spatial distance necessarily.
It can also there represent spatial
distance but it represents what it
represents. And the Lorent
transformations are transformations from
one set of coordinates to another set of
coordinates in which in both sets of
coordinates the form of d to squ is
equal to dt ^2 minus dx^2. Now I've
written it for two dimensions. What if
there are more dimensions of space as
there really are in the real world? Then
it will be d to squar is equal to dt ^2
minus dx^2 minus d y^2 minus dz^ 2 or
whatever if there are three coordinates
of
space. Okay.
So that's it. That's all you have to
know about special relativity. It's the
theory of
transformations which preserve a length
element which is a funny thing with a
minus sign in it. Now we're going to
assume that everybody knows that and
we're going to move on. What we're going
to say is supposing I introduce curved
coordinates into
spaceime. Have we ever seen any examples
of curved coordinates in spaceime in
this quarter so far?
Yeah, accelerated coordinates were
examples of curved coordinates in
spacetime. Remember I gave
you coordinates which look like this and
we also talked about coordinates which
were
accelerated. There's an example of uh
the uh of the introduction of curved
coordinates into spaceime for particular
purpose in order to study accelerated
coordinate systems. Okay. So, it's not
insane and not silly to introduce curved
coordinates into
spaceime. Uh, and if you do, what's
going to happen to this formula? What's
going to happen to this formula is the
same thing that happens to the formula
for distance between points when you
introduce curved coordinates into space.
Namely, you're going to get some new
coefficient functions. And the formula
is going to look
like well first of all
notation there are four coordinates of
spacetime tx y and z we're going to
label them x mu. Whenever you see a
Greek index as a uh as a um coordinate
index it always means that you're
talking about
spacetime. Okay. And how many what does
mu run over? Mu runs over four
possibilities, one of time and three
directions of
space. The usual
convention is not to call it x1 through
x4, but to call it
x0. I don't know how that got
started. Why x0 through x3 rather than
x1 through x4? I don't
know. with x0 being the time coordinate.
Time first.
Time first. Or you start with space. You
got one, two, three. What are you going
to do? Add four?
Why not add zero?
Yeah.
Right. If you decide you want to make
higher dimensional space times, you add
more space components. You never add
more time components. That's that's you
I mean you could play with that if you
like but uh
oh yeah sure
anyway so what's the what's the natural
generalization of this formula when you
introduce new sets of coordinates let's
call them y mu
now which also has a time component and
three space
components and assume that the ycoordin
ordinates and the xcoordinates are
related to each other by coordinate
transformation. Then what's the natural
analog or the generalization I should
say of the simple special relativity
formula?
It's exactly what you might expect. D to
squared is equal to G mu
new of now when I write just of X it
means of space and time a general
function of position in space time is
just written as a function of X without
specifying whether we're talking about
X0 X1 X2 X3 and so forth times dx mu dx
No, we don't need to have real
genuine curvature and gravity and so
forth to do this. We could just do this
by introducing curvy linear
coordinates for x and t.
So at the moment we haven't introduced
the theory of gravity when we say we can
write this down. We're just generalizing
the allowable coordinates that we can uh
that we can play
with. So that's uh that's the general
form of the proper time element between
two
points in spaceime where spacetime has a
metric tensor. Now what is the metric
tensor? Let's call these um let's call
these simple coordinates like this.
Let's call these, should we call them
cartisian?
Um, what's the right term for uh
h you have a name for them? Manowski.
Manowski. Good. Good. Manowski
coordinates. Yeah. Uh ordinary manowski
coordinates. And manowski coordinates
are not unique. Just like cartisian
coordinates are not unique. You can
rotate them. You can translate them. You
can lorent transform manowski
coordinates.
What's the manowski form for the metric
tensor? Well, it's clear. It's of the
form
one for the dt ^ 2 and -1 -1 -1 for the
dx^ 2. In other
words, it's a
matrix just like g was a matrix before.
the uh in flat coordinates.
Originally the metric was 1 one
one. What is it
now? It's a
one and three minus
ones with all zeros
elsewhere. Right? So a special case of a
metric p of a of a formula like this
would be where g
mu was simply 1 - 1 - 1 - one in which
case you would reproduce the usual
manowski proper time.
Okay. This symbol has a name. It's the
analog of
delta
MN. But it's not delta MN. It's not one
one one. It's one minus one - 1 - 1 -
one. It has a name. It's called
ATA. ATA MN Greek letter ADA. So ADA is
the metric of spacetime in Nowski
coordinates. And it's one minus one
minus one minus one minus one. And so we
could write in manowski type coordinates
the analog of cartisian coordinates d to
tao^ 2 is equal to ad
mu dx mu dx
new. Okay that's spacetime in a
nutshell. Almost everything we said
about tensors their transformation
properties is still correct.
G MU also allows you it has an inverse
again. So G mu has an inverse uh uh
matrix. G mu and its inverse allow you
to raise and lower indices. The
transformation properties of tensors are
identical to what they were uh
before. I'll write them again. You have
things like dx
mu which have a contravariant uh
structure. They're related to dy mu by
partial of y mu with respect to x new dx
new. So this defines the transformation
properties of contravariant indices.
It's exactly the same as it was before.
The transformation properties of tensors
are exactly what they were in the pure
space case. Don't have to change it not
at all for both contravariant and
covariant indices. The only thing is
that the metric tensor typically has
minuses as well as pluses in it. Now
what kind what are the special rules
about how many minuses and how many
pluses? We'll come to that. But this for
example is a special case. three minuses
and one
plus. Uh I'll be more precise about
what's an allowable tensor, an allowable
metric tensor, but for now the rules are
almost almost exactly the same with the
chronica delta being replaced by ADA.
When you did the
transformation x and y, you said y super
zero was the time dimension. What do you
mean by that? Just a definition of just
a notation. Okay. X super
tform the time. Yeah, you could do you
could do that. You can do it if you
like. You can do it if you like. It even
happens in some situations that you
might want to. Now, there is a rule.
I'll tell you I'll tell you what the
rule is now and we'll go through it
another time, but we need to we do need
to go through it. The rule is that gunu
gu is again a symmetric is a symmetric
tensor. Symmetric tensors have igen
values. They have a complete set of igen
values. They will always have four igen
values. Uh for an ordinary space those
igen values are all positive and it
corresponds to the fact that spatial
distances are always
positive. In relativity there is always
three negative and one positive value.
Right? If you're writing something down
which has not the right number of uh of
positive and negative igen values, you
have some sort of pathological space.
But we'll come to that. We'll come to
that. For now, the rules are really
unchanged. The rules are really
unchanged apart from the fact that uh
that a typical metric will have some
minus signs and some plus signs. And in
terms of igen values there are always
three negative ones and one positive one
which means is yeah am I right that is
inverse it is a tone inverse yeah just
like the chronica delta is right so the
ada with the upper indices is the same
as the ada with the lower indices right
uh right I'll go through this I will go
through this again but I just wanted to
since I was asked a question about how
to think about the geometry of an
expanding spaceime. Let me answer it
right now. It's we have everything we
need now to write it to uh to express
it in a general
spaceime. These metric components are
functions of all of the uh all of the
all of the
coordinates. Uh, a particularly simple
kind of spacetime is one where the
coordinates where where the metric only
depends on time and doesn't depend on
space. That's the sort of situation you
have when space is
homogeneous. If space is homogeneous,
everywhere the same. That's a typical
cosmological setup where space is
everywhere is the same. Apart of course
when I say it's everywhere is the same I
mean on very large scales on scales much
bigger than galaxies and so forth. Space
is the same one place as another. The
metric doesn't depend on space but it
does depend on time and that time
dependence is the uh the expansion of
the universe. So let me write down for
you a particular metric and then just
look at it a little
bit. It corresponds to g
munu is equal instead of
Instead of 1 - 1 - 1 - one let's write
1 0 0
0. Now instead of minus one let's write
minus a of t where a of t is time
dependent.
0 0
0 - a of t 0 and 0 0 0 minus a of
t one function a of t just one function
and that function is called the scale
factor. What this means is that the
proper time or the line interval is d t
^2 minus a of t squared
dx^2 dx^2 + d y^2 + dz
^2.
Um, it may not be obvious to
you, but this spacetime with a time
dependence here is very different than
flat spacetime. To show you the kind of
difference, supposing we did something
similar with space. Incidentally, this
is the characteristic metric. If a of t
is an expanding function of time, if
it's an increasing function of time,
uh then that then that's called an
expanding
universe. Right? I'll come back to this,
but let me just show you qualitatively
what this means by giving you the analog
for ordinary space. Let's just think
about two dimensions of space. And let
me imagine one of the directions is an
angular direction. We've already done
things like that. We we considered d r 2
+ r 2 d theta
2 d r 2 + r 2 d theta 2. That's somewhat
similar to this. The r 2 is like
dt^2 and r 2 itself is like a 2. It's a
function of t. a is a function of t.
Here r is a fun r is a function of r or
r squ is a function of r. So there's a a
similarity between this formula
here dt ^2 minus a of t ^2 dx^2 and the
r 2 + r 2 d theta^ 2. Now what is the
space time here? Oh sorry what is the
space here?
It's a plane. It's just polar
coordinates. It's a plane. It's flat
spacetime and it's just looking at that
spacetime in polar coordinates. But now
supposing instead of just r 2 I put some
general function of r in. First before
putting a general function in let's put
in another specific function sine of r
squared. What is this space now?
That's a sphere. And the way to think
about it now is
that the distance around the well the
distance around the theta axis depends
on r in a characteristic way. Here's the
sphere. Let's think of r
as r is now like the polar angle.
And as you go around the sphere or as
you go around the theta
direction, theta I'm having go this way
now. I think I've turned the sphere on
its side for some odd odd reason. Uh why
did I do that? Stupid. Let's put it
let's stand it up again.
[Music]
uh theta goes around this way and r is
just replacing what I called phi
before right what's happening is instead
of sine of r just increasing like r it
increases and then it decreases s is a
function which increases and then
decreases right it increases from zero
to pi / two and then decreases. That's
why the sphere increases and then
decreases, right? It starts growing as
you move away from the south pole. It
starts growing but then shrinks
again. That sphere of course is not a
flat spacetime. If I only had R squared
here, it would be like looking
at just a plane.
with sin squared here it's more
complicated and it's
curved okay supposing I put an arbitrary
function some kind of
function which
um I don't know let's put uh an
exponential function here e to the 2r
what kind of space would that look
like it would look like a horn yeah it
would look like a by a horn I mean you
know toot toot
the distance around the theta axis would
grow exponentially and it would look
like
that. Now it's not growing with time,
it's growing with r. So this would be
some kind of space which had the
property that as you move away from r
equals 0, r equals 0 was over here. It
grows and it grows rapidly, grows
exponentially.
supposing I put in I don't know you
could put in all kinds of things
uh I don't know e to the 2r * uh time uh
oh I don't know some arbitrary function
which grows and at the same time
oscillates it grows and oscillates at
the same time well you can make very
complicated kinds of spaces
which look like
that they're just surfaces. But the
character of the surface and the way
that it grows as you move away from r
equals z depends on this function f of
r. Most of these spaces are not flat.
They have curvature of all kinds that
we'll talk about next time. But that's
exactly what this a of t does here. It
creates a space-time which as a function
of time the spacetime grows grows
shrinks does whatever whatever it does
can do all kinds of wiggles and instead
of r this would be t. So this is the
metric of a timed dependent spacetime
and if a is a growing function then it's
it's an expanding spacetime. That's all
it means to say that
spacetime is expanding in this language
in this language of a metric
tensor. Uh we'll come back to
it next time. We'll talk about curvature
and parallel
transport and uh try to get to the
Einstein
[Music]
equations. The proceeding program is
copyrited by Stanford University. Please
visit us at stanford.edu.